let's now look at the solution for part
1 of this quiz which is asking when do
these four instructions dispatch and
write their results we will do that one
instruction at a time the load is issued
in cycle 1 it doesn't have any
dependencies but we know that it cannot
dispatch in the same cycle when it's
issued so it will dispatch in cycle 2
the load takes one cycle to do so it
will write its result in the very next
cycle the multiplication instruction is
issued in cycle 2 it will dispatch in
cycle 3 or later because it cannot issue
and then dispatch in cycle 2 it will
dispatch either in cycle 3 or whenever
its operands become available and
because this multiply instruction
doesn't depend on the load here it uses
F 0 and F 1 and the load produces F 6
that means that this instruction has all
the operands ready as soon as it issues
so it can dispatch in cycle 3 it
couldn't issue and then dispatch in
cycle 2 because of the same thing issue
and and dispatch in this processor is
not allowed the multiplication takes 5
cycles to do so if it dispatches in
cycle 3 to execute it's going to be
broadcasting its result in cycle 8 the
add here is issued in cycle 3 so again
it cannot dispatch in the same cycle but
it could dispatch in cycle 4 if all of
its operands are available in that cycle
however it needs F 2 and F 6 these are
produced by load and multiplied here so
actually it will not be able to dispatch
in cycle 4 because the multiplier result
is only available in cycle 8 so what is
going to happen to this instruction is
it's going to wait and capture its
result in cycle 8 and then it cannot
capture and then dispatch in the same
cycle so it will dispatch in the
cycle which is cycle nine because this
is an ad and had a latency of one cycle
it will write its result in cycle 10 for
this ad here it issues in cycle four it
becomes eligible for dispatch in cycle
five if its operands are ready but they
are not
it needs the f2 produced by the
multiplication and the f6 produced by
decide that means that it will capture
its last missing operand at the later of
these two cycles which is cycle ten so
in cycle 10 this instruction captures
its last missing operand which is f6 and
then it cannot dispatch in that same
cycle because of this so it dispatches
in cycle 11 and finishes in cycle 12 and
this completes the first part of the
quiz